okay so today I want to try to introduce
another concept this concepts that think
a little tricky so for the last half
I'll also try to give a concrete example
which luckily enough
I've happened upon recently in it but in
conversation with the team behind this
particular concrete example and I think
it's awesome there's also a great
example so the concept I'm going to use
the term the transcendent operator now I
don't know if anybody else uses that
term I'm hoping not because that way
it's not going to be confused but the
the basic idea and I think I'm kind of
maybe stealing the idea for my friend
Jeff Gomez in the context of transmedia
so so here's the idea you have some kind
of object which is very abstract and the
the abstraction describes the object in
a way that is in some sense specifically
its uniqueness or its characteristics
its necessary characteristics its unique
and singular characteristics but
separate from any particular
actualization or instantiation like an
instance so in computer science we could
think of it as an object class and then
we could talk about an instance of an
object class where the specific
characteristics are in fact given values
in the context of transmedia so Jeff's
domain we can think of like in the
Marvel Cinematic Universe you have this
notion of say Thor and they have a
problem which is that they need to be
able to empower into the director of the
Avengers to make Thor like to do Thor
and they needed to power the director of
the of the movie Thor to do throw these
are actually very different people with
different aesthetics different
sensibilities different stories
different requirements and yet of course
the character needs to be felt as being
Thor the same person right continuity
across distinct instantiations distinct
contexts and so that's the object or the
intent of a transcendent operators be
able to create something and to enable
it to have content
newah tea while also having specificity
or uniqueness in distinct contexts all
right now what does that mean in the
context of Scipio okay
so the notion of sevilla is very very
much tied to this idea of the
transcendent operator so i'll give you
an example and then I'll tie this
example to the to the concreting to the
concrete real world example it's
happening
we have a transcendent operator that
describes the characteristics what I'll
call the ontological design of Sevilla
which is to say the the aspects of
living this the the physical
architectural elements things like how
people living in sitting them deal with
problems of energy how do they get
energy or waste or food or
transportation or physical domicile and
things like that all the different
questions you have to ask to answer the
problem of how do we live together in
community in space there's a there's a
set of design characteristics of what a
an instantiation of Sevilla must look
like and then what happens is is you
actually instantiate an actual sibian in
a real context in a real bio region
specifically so each distinct sibian
will have its transcendent
characteristics in common across the
globe but in particular unique bio
regions will have very specific
different instantiations right so if I
were to instantiate a Sevilla min say
the desert and then instantiate a
Sevilla min like Oregon on the coast of
Oregon those are of course in many many
ways going to be quite different because
the the actual ways that they will
answer questions like how to resource
food water will be different but they'll
also have a lot of similarities and I
don't mean just generically that they
both will have to source food in water
but things like how do you that what was
the set of toolkits that you might bring
to bear in general across all possible
solutions at least now for enabling
closed loops and so one of the
characteristics of a sybian construct is
to close as many loops as possible so
there's one answer to the question of
closed loops water
in the desert there's another answer to
the question of closed-loop closed-loop
water and Oregon and both of those
answers sort of take the basic toolkit
and apply some of this some of that
together and and solve the problem
answer the question well and of course
you go across the entire set of
questions in a living space so the the
the civvie InDesign or in fact the
transcendent design is is a problem of
designing at the level of the
transcendent operator in in the mode of
what we might call architecture or
physical design questions like energy
and food in the mode of culture and in
the mode of like socio technology things
like governments in economic which is
not strictly the same and I would say
the cultures probably the most
fundamental so doing the transcendent
operator around culture and then and
then the process for instantiating that
in given specific actualizations is the
most fundamental work the example I'm
going to give is actually an example
from the level of architecture and
systems design but so let's move on to
the example
okay so the the actual real-world
project that I've come into contact with
recently is called Oceanics and what
I'll do is I'll be using the the actual
concept design by the vrk ingles group
to help articulate the concepts when I
ran into the team at Oceanics and I've
done that with him several times I was
taken by the degree to which it really
is very similar to a lot of the cilium
notions particularly if you were to
imagine it as a an instantiation of this
idiom transcendent operator in the
context of the ocean particularly ocean
30 degrees north and south of the
Equator with a big lean towards the
physical layer so so let's take a look
at that so the first thing that they did
is they take a look at the whole system
and the the set of holistic requirements
that are necessary to actually make a
given instance of Oceanics complete
right so you have to be able to take
care of food and you have to take care
of water and add it at a design level at
the very high level things like
sustainability and localism and lack of
waste are all and living this by the way
wholesomeness are all key values that
feed into the design and then they run a
process where they take a look at how do
we express these values given the
limitations and the capacities of the
local environment
what they do is they have what they call
a kit of parts so they took a look at
each particular problem say for example
food or energy and then they look
through all the different possible
answers to that problem and then they
took a look at which of those answers
are most valid and least valid in the
context both at the local environment
and in the context of the larger whole
so for example in the case of oceanic so
if you've got floating platforms in the
ocean you have access to ocean tidal
power to produce electricity obviously
in the context of the broader Sylvia
MIFF your instantiate eNOS idiom in the
desert you don't but if you're in Stan
shooting it in the desert perhaps you
have a the ability to rely on solar
power more effectively so now let's take
a look at the structural design and this
is where my eyes were really opened in
terms of the relationship between what
they're doing at Oceanics and the
Scythian vision they've taken a what was
frankly a fractal and Hellenic approach
okay so if we take a look at this basic
unit which they call a neighborhood as
you can see it's actually designed
around roughly the level of the Dunbar
number and it's designed around the
ability to have a a decent fraction of
the whole of life happening in a given
neighborhood so the neighborhood has
food and water and waste and power
electricity and education and human
development and vocation anchored and
grounded at the at the neighborhood
level then a series of neighborhoods is
collected into the next fractal level up
the village so in each transformation
each ilanic level up you have a really
interesting dialogue between generality
and specificity or uniqueness so for
example any given neighborhood will have
a sizeable fraction of self-sufficiency
it'll produce a sizeable fraction wits
and food is an energy etc etc but then
also will have a meaningful fraction of
dependence on other neighborhoods in its
village and uniqueness respess
officially so in the context of a given
village for example you may have one
neighborhood
leans more heavily in the direction of
say food so it's kind of like the
restaurant district another one leads
more in the direction of say art or
research and and and industry and and so
you get this really nice tension between
resilience self-sufficiency decoupling
and specialization and intensity and and
by the way also communication as people
you know if I never leave my
neighborhood then what happens is I not
creating a parochialism but if I leave
my neighborhood to go to another
neighborhood in the same village because
they have something that my neighborhood
doesn't have then of course this creates
flow and creates a felt sense of
connection then villages for their part
can be connected up into into cities
start getting into larger population
densities you know you'll notice by the
way at the level of the city you also
started seeing the interesting addition
of stochastic or asymmetric elements
elements that are not strictly the
hexagon and that's an important aspect
as well right so an increase in the
richness or diversity of the
characteristic while also maintaining
the symmetry at the primary
characteristic and of course as you get
into larger populations the degree to
which you might have for example a given
village may have a real lien given
direction you know it's it's a
gastronome village or it's a village
that is sort of renowned for its
athletics where where the the larger
city now has even stronger
differentiation in principle this
construct continued to scale so you
could get a population of Manhattan in a
city 'm as Arion Oceanics of adequate
size and what's fascinating is the
actual size isn't that vast particularly
in the context of the ocean but has a
vastly better physical layout for for
living this we'll take a look at some of
those the way that feels in second
returning back to some of the principles
you can see that we have for example an
intent to rely as much as possible on
locally sourced
and either recyclable or regenerative
materials and to engage in wood in the
Oceanics context is what we would call
regenerative agriculture or regenerative
permaculture in general so we have a
vision that talks about how the building
out of this new way this kind of cool
fun interesting new concept can also be
used as a bridge to instantiate a whole
bunch of values that we won't want to
see in general and by weaving these
values together you actually get a
really meaningful chance of of actualize
in them in reality so then we can look
at the the felt sense the sense of
living this and I think Engels did a
great job here of creating some visual
images that capture things like
wholesomeness and connectedness and
living a right relationship with nature
you notice for example if the buildings
are at least in this particular
instantiation constructed out of bamboo
and with an intent that the bamboo can
be removed and replaced and regrown and
delivered back into the environment by
closed loops everywhere you look as much
as you can and then finally the notion
of specificity or already in the context
of Oceanics the the necessity and the
capacity for true actualization of the
transcendent operator differentially
based on different bioregions
or different locations different
contexts so for example if you were to
actualize it in the ocean but the ocean
next to her near say the arab peninsula
there's going to be one set of
characteristics that will apply and if
we were to actualize it in the ocean
near say a more northern clime country
the different set of characteristics
apply iein so that's that toolkit the
mission of the kid of parts or the
notion of the transcendent operator
combining with the process for
actualization in a given context giving
rise to events that are simultaneously
specific and unique and yet also have a
sentence felt sense of continuity with
each other so that's a sense of this
notion of the transcendent operator and
it's
actualization in a given context
obviously in the context of
the ocean for Oceanics and you can
imagine that same basic process applied
in other bio regions you can imagine it
being applied in in in the desert you
can apply it in Cascadia you could apply
it in the you know equatorial
rainforests etc and in each case the the
point always the hope of the CBM model
is that there would be a very important
local distinctness right there's a real
difference coming up to the local
environment local materials the local
characteristics that have constraints
like Sun and rain and whatnot and yet
also a very distinct sense of sameness
and continuity so that a given cilium
would have a sense of translate ability
and connectedness with any other given
Sevilla while maintaining that distinct
sense of difference and the creative
gradient the results and one other
takeaway this particular presentation is
the possibility that the potential
Oceanics is it's a real project and
frankly it's it's it's it could be done
like it's really a matter of financing
and frankly not that much financing to
build a neighborhood right for the very
first time ever and then of course once
they've built the first neighborhood you
can start building the second and the
third and the fourth and begin to
replicate it and it really really pushes
the bar in terms of of the kinds of
living miss we can create I mean the
ability to to deal with a lot of the
problems that we want to deal with the
problems like well for example just
waste or energy how do we produce the
the food we want and also problems of
community and in culture and how do we
actually live more real grounded
wholesome humane lives there's a lot of
pent-up possibility right the reality is
is that one of the reasons why CBM is
right is we've been sitting on an old
construct in these sort of 19th century
cities grossed up and hypertrophied by a
virtue of the technologies of the 20th
the 21st century
this like a stretched rubber band and if
we if we just pop into a new model with
these smart villages constructed in this
fractal and whole onic structure there's
a lot of possibility that we can we can
leap to we can leapfrog into a very
distinct space